While an if statement works well for checking
a condition, many logic flows within an app
need to check for multiple possibilities for
conditions and then perform an action based on
which condition in a set of conditions is true.
For example, in a situation in which a person
playing a game reaches level two after reaching
10000 points but also reaches level one after
reaching 5000 points, we want to next figure out
how to get the correct actions to take place based
on multiple conditions or multiple possibilities
within a condition. In this 212-elif code example,
the score is stored in a variable on line 1. Then,
we have two if statements, starting on lines 3 and
5. One if statement looks for a score over 10000
and the other a score over 5000. I will run this
code. The second statement was printed. Through
going back and analyzing this code, that makes
sense because the score is set to 8000, meaning it
is not over 10000, so this print statement on line
4 should not run. The print statement on line
6 should run as the score is over 5000. Let’s
change the score from 8000 to 18000 and test this
code again. The statement on line 4 is printed as
the score is over 10000. But, the statement on
line 6 was printed as well. Do we want to remind
someone they reached level 1 in a game when
they’ve already reached level 2? Probably not.
This situation brings us to a common programming
need: to have a single if statement with multiple
possibilities and just have one result based
on which condition ends up being true. It’s
like saying this: I will go to the beach if
it’s sunny outside and over 80 degrees, but
if it’s just sunny, I will take a walk. The code
equivalent in Python for such a situation is elif,
short for else if. I will change the if on line
5 to an elif. Within an if statement, the code is
exited on the first match. Thus, now we are saying
if the score is over 10000, print line 4. Else,
if the score is over 5000, meaning it’s not
over 10000, print line 6. I will rerun the code,
and we only get the print statement on line 4,
so the adjustment worked. Let’s ensure this code
works when I lower the score to 8000. It does
work. When learning about conditions in code,
it is essential to know what the code is to go
through a condition with multiple possibilities
so that the output is not cluttered with
unnecessary results. In this situation,
we are testing the same variable multiple
times with a desired output of one result,
so we need the elif statement to represent the
else if. There is no set limit to the number of
elifs in code, so you could theoretically have a
different message for many different score levels.